<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF8'?>
<epigraphs>
<epigraph id="epigraph4">
<content>
<p>Venerable Ānanda approached the Blessed One, paid homage, sat down to one
side, and said to him:</p>
<p>“Venerable sir, this is half of the holy life, that is, good friendship,
good companionship, good comradeship.”</p>
<p>“Not so, Ānanda! Not so, Ānanda! This is the entire holy life, Ānanda, that
is, good friendship, good companionship, good comradeship. When a bhikkhu has a
good friend, a good companion, a good comrade, it is to be expected that he
will develop and cultivate the Noble Eightfold Path.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn45.2</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph1">
<content>
<p>If you have no satisfactory teacher, then take this sure Dhamma and practice
it. For the Dhamma is sure, and when it is rightly undertaken it will be to
your welfare and happiness for a long time.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn60</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph2">
<content>
<p>The Buddha said to the monks: “Imagine that the whole earth was covered with
water, and that a man was to throw a yoke with a hole in it into the water.
Blown by the wind, that yoke would drift north, south, east and west. Now
suppose that once in a hundred years a blind turtle was to rise to the surface.
What would be the chances of that turtle putting his head through the hole in
the yoke?” “It would be very unlikely, Lord.” “Well, it is just as unlikely
that one will be born as a human being. It is just as unlikely that a
Tathāgata, a Noble One, a fully enlightened Buddha, should appear in the world.
And it is just as unlikely that the Dhamma and discipline of the Tathāgata
should be proclaimed.”</p>
</content>
<uid>sn56.47-48</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph3">
<content>
<blockquote class="gatha">
<p>The doors of the Deathless are open.<br/>
Let those who can hear establish their faith.</p>
</blockquote>
</content>
<uid>mn26</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph5">
<content>
<p>Unsurpassed is the Lord’s way of teaching the Dhamma concerning one’s proper
moral conduct. One should be honest and faithful, without deception, chatter,
hinting or belittling, not always ready to add gain to gain, but with the
sense-doors guarded, moderate in food, a promoter of peace, observant, active
and strenuous in effort, a meditator, mindful, with proper conversation,
steady-going, resolute and sensible, not hankering after sense pleasures, but
mindful and prudent. This is the unsurpassed teaching concerning a person’s
proper ethical conduct.</p>
</content>
<uid>dn28</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph6">
<content>
<p>“What do you think about this?” said the Lord. “What is the purpose of a
mirror?” “It is for the purpose of reflection, sir”, replied Rāhula. “Even so,
an action to be done by body, speech or mind should only be done after careful
reflection.”</p>
</content>
<uid>mn61</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph8">
<content>
<p>As long as the Tathāgata, the Noble One, the fully enlightened Buddha, has
not come to be, there is no shining forth of great light, no great radiance.
Only darkness and blindness prevail. There is no proclaiming, no teaching, no
explaining, no setting forth, no opening up, no analysis of or illuminating of
the Four Noble Truths. But when the Tathāgata, the Noble One, the fully
enlightened Buddha has come to be, there is a shining forth of great light, of
great radiance; darkness and blindness are no more. There is a proclaiming, a
teaching, an explaining, a setting forth, an opening up, an analysis, an
illuminating of the Four Noble Truths.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn56.37</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph9">
<content>
<p>What is the Noble Eightfold Path? It is Right View, Right Thought, Right
Speech, Right Action, Right Livelihood, Right Effort, Right Mindfulness and
Right Samādhi.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn45.8</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph12">
<content>
<p>Just as the great ocean has one taste, the taste of salt, even so, this
Dhamma has one taste too, the taste of freedom.</p>
</content>
<uid>an8.20</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph15">
<content>
<p>What sort of Dhamma practice leads to great good for oneself? Concerning
this, the noble disciple reflects: ‘Here am I, fond of life, not wishing to
die, fond of pleasure and averse to pain. If someone killed me, I would not
like it. Likewise, if I were to kill someone they would not like it. For what
is unpleasant to me must be unpleasant to another, so how could I inflict
unpleasantness on them?’ As a result of such reflection one abstains from
killing, encourages others to abstain from it and speaks in praise of such
abstaining.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn55.7</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph16">
<content>
<p>Greed is to be slightly blamed but it is slow to change. Hatred is to be
greatly blamed but it is quick to change. Delusion is to be greatly blamed and
it is slow to change.</p>
</content>
<uid>an3.68</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph17">
<content>
<p>There are these four kinds of happiness to be enjoyed by a householder who
enjoys sense pleasures from time to time and when occasion offers. What four?
The happiness of ownership, the happiness of wealth, the happiness of freedom
from debt and the happiness of blamelessness. And what is the happiness of
ownership? Concerning this, a householder has wealth acquired by energetic
striving, won by strength of arm and sweat of brow, justly and lawfully. When
he thinks of this he feels happiness and satisfaction. And what is the
happiness of wealth? Concerning this, a householder has wealth justly and
lawfully acquired, and he does many good works with it. When he thinks of this
he feels happiness and satisfaction. And what is the happiness of freedom from
debt? Concerning this, a householder owes no debts large or small to anyone,
and when he thinks of this he feels happiness and satisfaction. And what is the
happiness of blamelessness? Concerning this, the noble disciple is blessed with
blameless action of body, speech and mind, and when he thinks of this he feels
happiness and satisfaction.</p>
</content>
<uid>an4.61</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph19">
<content>
<p>There are these four types of people found in the world. What four? Those
who are concerned neither with their own good nor the good of others, those who
are concerned with good of others but not their own, those concerned with their
own good but not that of others, and those who are concerned with both their
own good and the good of others. Just as a stick from a funeral pyre, burning
at both ends and smeared with dung in the middle, serves no useful purpose as
fuel in the village or as timber in the forest—using such a simile do I speak
of those concerned neither with their own good nor the good of the others.
Those concerned with the good of others but not their own are more excellent
and higher than this. Those who are concerned with their own good but not that
of others are more excellent and higher still. But those who are concerned with
both their own good and the good of others—they are, of these four persons, the
supreme, the highest the topmost and the best.</p>
</content>
<uid>an4.95</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph20">
<content>
<p>These ten things nourish the ten things that are desirable, liked, charming
and hard to win in the world. What ten? Energy and exertion nourish wealth.
Finery and adornment nourish beauty. Doing things at the proper time nourishes
health. Friendship with the beautiful nourishes virtue. Restraint of the senses
nourishes the holy life. Not quarrelling nourishes friendship. Repetition
nourishes great knowledge. Listening carefully and asking questions nourishes
wisdom. Study and examination nourishes the Dhamma. And living rightly
nourishes rebirth in the heaven realm.</p>
</content>
<uid>an10.73</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph21">
<content>
<p>If a fool was sitting in an assembly hall, in the main street or at the
crossroads and people were to talk about him, and if he were one who broke the
Five Precepts, he would think: ‘These people are talking about me because I
have done these things.’ This is the first kind of anguish and dejection that
the fool experiences here and now. Again, a fool might see the king arrest a
thief or a wrongdoer and punish him. Upon seeing this, the fool would think:
‘The king is punishing that wrongdoer. Now, I have done these things also, so
if the king were to know about me, he might punish me too.’ This is the second
kind of anguish and dejection that the fool experiences here and now. And
further, while the fool is sitting in a chair, lying on a bed or on the ground,
those evil deeds that he has previously done with body, speech or mind, come to
rest on him, lie on him, settle on him, just as when at evening, the shadows of
the great mountains come to rest, lie and settle on the ground. At such times,
the fool thinks: ‘Oh indeed, what is beautiful and skillful has not been done
by me. I have made no refuge against the fearful. There is a place for those
who have not done good but only evil, and to there I will go.’ And so he
grieves, mourns, laments, beats his breast, cries and falls into
disillusionment. This is the third kind of anguish and dejection that the fool
experiences here and now.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn129</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>


<epigraph id="epigraph25">
<content>
<p>Believers can be recognized by three things. What three? They desire to see
those who are virtuous, they desire to hear the good Dhamma, and with a heart
free from stinginess, they live at home with the mind cleaned of meanness,
open-handed, pure-handed, delighting in sharing, being one to ask a favour of,
being one who rejoices in giving.</p>
</content>
<uid>an3.42</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph26">
<content>
<p>The Lord acts as he speaks, and he speaks as he acts. Except for the Buddha,
we find no teacher as consistent as this, whether we survey the past or the
present.</p>
</content>
<uid>n/a</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph32">
<content>
<p>The holy life is not lived for the advantages that come from gains, honours
or fame; it is not lived for the advantages that come from morality; it is not
lived for the advantages that come from samādhi, nor is it lived for the
advantages that come from knowledge and vision. But that which is unshakable
freedom of mind—that is the aim of the holy life, that is the goal, that is
it’s culmination.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn29</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph34">
<content>
<p>In giving food, one gives five things. What five? One gives life, beauty,
happiness, strength and intelligence. And in giving these things, one partakes
in the qualities of life, beauty, happiness, strength and intelligence, both
here and hereafter.</p>
</content>
<uid>an5.37</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph36">
<content>
<p>By defilement of mind, beings are defiled; by purification of mind, beings
are purified.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn22.100</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph37">
<content>
<p>Develop the meditation called mindfulness of in-and-out breathing because it
is of great fruit, of great advantage. And how is mindfulness of in-and-out
breathing developed, how is it made much of, how is it of great fruit, great
advantage? Concerning this, one who has gone to the forest, to the root of a
tree or to an empty place, sits down cross-legged with the back straight,
establishing mindfulness in front of him. Mindfully one breathes in, mindfully
one breathes out. Breathing in a long breath one knows: ‘I am breathing in a
long breath;’ breathing out a long breath one knows: ‘I am breathing out a long
breath.’ Breathing in a short breath one knows: ‘I am breathing in a short
breath;’ breathing out a short breath one knows: ‘I am breathing out a short
breath.’ One trains oneself, thinking: ‘Breathing in I shall experience the
whole body.’ One trains oneself, thinking: ‘Breathing out I shall experience
the whole body.’ One trains oneself, thinking: ‘Breathing in I will
tranquillize bodily activities.’ One trains oneself, thinking: ‘Breathing out I
will tranquillize bodily activities.’</p>
</content>
<uid>mn62</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph39">
<content>
<p>Those families where the mother and father are worshipped in the home are
said to be like Brahmā, like teachers of old, they are ranked with the ancient
gods. Truly worthy of offerings are those families where the mother and father
are worshipped in the home. ‘Brahmā,’ ‘teachers of old,’ ‘teachers of old,’
‘gods of old,’ and ‘worthy of offerings’ are terms for a mother and father. And
why is this? Because a mother and father do much for their children—they bring
them up, nourish them and introduce them to the world.</p>
</content>
<uid>an4.63</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph40">
<content>
<p>There are these five strands of sense pleasure. What five? Material shapes
cognizable with the eye, pleasant, liked, enticing, connected with sensual
pleasures, alluring. Sounds cognizable with the ear, smells cognizable with the
nose, tastes cognizable with the tongue, and touches cognizable with the body,
all of them agreeable, pleasant, liked, enticing, connected with sensual
pleasures, alluring. These are the five strands of sense pleasure.</p>
<p>Whatever happiness or joy arises as a result of these five strands of sense
pleasure, that is called the happiness of sense of pleasure. It is a common
happiness, a happiness of the average person, an ignoble happiness. It should
not be pursued, developed or emphasized. It is a happiness to be feared, I
say.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn66</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph41">
<content>
<p>One who does these things is called a master of the pathways of thought. The
thought he wants to think, he thinks; the thought he does not want to think, he
does not think. He has cut off craving, removed the fetters, mastered pride and
put an end to suffering.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn20</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph43">
<content>
<p>Having seen a shape with the eye, smelt a smell with the nose, savored a
taste with the tongue, felt a touch with the body or cognized a thought with
the mind, one is not entranced by its general appearance or its detail. For if
one lived with the sense organs uncontrolled, attraction, repulsion and evil
unskilled states of mind would grow. So, one controls the sense organs, and
having this noble control of the sense organs, one experiences the happiness of
being unruffled.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn51</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph45">
<content>
<p>The Lord said to the monks who were quarrelling: “If animals can be
courteous, deferential and polite to each other so should you be.”</p>
</content>
<uid>pi-tv-kd16</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph46">
<content>
<p>This samādhi on in-and-out breathing, if cultivated and developed, is
something peaceful and excellent, something perfect in itself and also a
pleasant way of living. It dispels evil thoughts that have arisen, and makes
them vanish in a moment. It is just as when, in the last month of the hot
season, the dust and dirt fly up and suddenly a great shower of rain lays it
and makes it settle in a moment.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn54.9</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph47">
<content>
<p>When a good person is reborn into a family, it is for the welfare, the
happiness and the benefit of many—for that person’s parents, their spouse and
children, their servants and workers, and their friends and companions.</p>
</content>
<uid>an5.42</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph51">
<content>
<p>Sīha asked the Lord: “Is it possible, Lord, to see the results of
generosity?” And the Lord said: “Yes, it is possible to see the results of
generosity. The giver, the generous one, is liked and dear to many. This is a
result of generosity that is observable. Good and wise people follow the
generous person. This is a result of generosity that is observable. The
generous person earns a good reputation. This also is a result of generosity
that is observable. Once again, in whatever company he enters, be it nobles,
brahmins, householders or monks, the generous person enters with confidence and
without trouble. This is a result of giving that is observable. And finally,
the giver, the generous person, is reborn in heaven after death. This is a
result of generosity that can only be seen hereafter.”</p>
</content>
<uid>an5.34</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph53">
<content>
<p>Akkosaka of the Bhāradvāja clan came to know that the leader of the clan had
joined the Saṅgha of the monk Gotama. Angry and displeased, he went to where
the Lord was and reviled and abused him with rude, harsh words. When he had
finished, the Lord said: “What do you think, brahmin? … Do you sometimes offer
food to guests?”—“Yes, Gotama, sometimes I do.”</p>
<p>“And if they do not accept these things from you, whose do these things
become?”—“They become mine.”</p>
<p>“It is the same here, brahmin. That with which you revile, scold and abuse
me, who does not revile, scold or abuse you, that I do not accept from you. It
is yours, brahmin, it belongs to you.”</p>
</content>
<uid>sn7.2</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph54">
<content>
<p>Sense desire is an obstruction and a hindrance which enshrouds the mind and
weakens wisdom. Ill-will, sloth and torpor, restlessness and worry and doubt
are all obstructions and hindrances which enshroud the mind and weaken wisdom.
Surely it is possible that one, after abandoning these obstructions and
hindrances which grow in and up over the mind and weaken wisdom, being strong
in wisdom, should know his own good, the good of others, the good of both, and
attain that knowledge and vision befitting the Noble Ones and transcending
human states.</p>
</content>
<uid>an5.51</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph55">
<content>
<p>Just as a pot without support is easily upset while one with support is
difficult to upset, in the same way, the mind without support is easily upset
and the mind with support is difficult to upset. And what is the support of the
mind? It is the Noble Eightfold Path: Right View, Right Thought, Right Speech,
Right Action, Right Livelihood, Right Effort, Right Mindfulness and Right
Samādhi.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn45.27</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph56">
<content>
<p>When a cloth that is stained and dirty cloth is dipped in green, yellow, red
or crimson dye, it will not be properly dyed. And why? Because it is not clean.
In the same way, a bad destiny can be expected when the mind is stained. When a
cloth that is quite clean and is dipped in green, yellow, red or crimson dye,
it will be properly dyed. And why? Because it is clean. In the same way, a good
destiny may be expected when the mind is pure.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn7</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph57">
<content>
<p>One who would rightly use the terms ‘noble way of life,’ ‘sublime state,’
‘the Tathāgata’s way of life’ would do so to describe the samādhi on in-and-out
breathing.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn54.11</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph63">
<content>
<p>Giving up lying, one becomes a speaker of the truth, reliable, trustworthy,
dependable, not a deceiver of the world. Giving up slander, one does not repeat
there what is heard here, or repeat here what is heard there, for the purpose
of causing divisions between people. Thus, one becomes a reconciler of those
who are divided and a combiner of those already united. Rejoicing in peace,
delighting in peace, promoting peace; peace becomes the motive of his speech.
Giving up harsh speech, one speaks what is blameless, pleasant to the ear,
agreeable, going to the heart, urbane, pleasing, and liked by all. Giving up
useless chatter, one speaks at the right time, about the facts, to the point,
about Dhamma and discipline, words worthy of being treasured up, seasonable,
reasonable, clearly defined and connected to the goal.</p>
</content>
<uid>dn2</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph65">
<content>
<p>Once, the Lord dwelt among the Sakyas in the Park of the Banyan Tree at
Kapilavatthu, and while there, Mahānāma the Sakyan came to him and asked: “How,
Lord, does one become a lay disciple?”</p>
<p>“When one has taken refuge in the Buddha, the Dhamma, and the Saṅgha, then
one is a lay disciple.”</p>
<p>“How, Lord, is a disciple virtuous?”</p>
<p>“When a lay disciple abstains from killing, stealing, sexual misconduct,
lying and drinking intoxicants, then he is virtuous.”</p>
</content>
<uid>an8.25</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph67">
<content>
<p>Whatever one thinks about and ponders over often, one’s mind gets a leaning
in that way.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn19</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph69">
<content>
<p>How is there a threefold cleaning of the body? Concerning this, one abandons
killing, lays aside the stick and the sword and lives with care, kindness and
compassion towards all living beings. One abandons stealing the property of
anyone, whether in the jungle or the village; things not given, one does not
steal. One abandons sexual misconduct. One has no intercourse with girls under
the guardianship of their mother or father, their brother, sister or relatives,
with girls lawfully protected, those already pledged to a husband, those
undergoing punishment or those dressed with garlands and promised in
marriage.</p>
</content>
<uid>an10.176</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph71">
<content>
<p>The lord asked: “Which is greater? The little sand on my fingernail, or the
great Earth?”</p>
<p>“Lord, greater by far is the great Earth. Tiny is the sand on your
fingernail. The two cannot be compared.”</p>
<p>“So too, beings who are reborn as humans are few in number. Far greater are
those who are reborn in non-human realms. Therefore, you should train yourself,
thinking: ‘We will live earnestly.’”</p>
</content>
<uid>sn20.2</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph75">
<content>
<p>If you take refuge in the Buddha, the Dhamma and the Saṅgha, no fear or
trembling will ever arise.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn11.4</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph76">
<content>
<p>These four states conduce to the growth of wisdom, they are of great help to
one who has become human. What four? Association with a good person, hearing
the good Dhamma, wise attention, and behaving in accordance with the
Dhamma.</p>
</content>
<uid>an4.249</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph80">
<content>
<p>That which is called mind, mentality or consciousness arises and disappears
continuously both day and night. Just as a monkey swinging through the trees
grabs one branch, letting it go only to grab another, so too that which is
called mind, mentality or consciousness arises and disappears continuously both
day and night.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn12.61</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph84">
<content>
<p>One who sees the Dhamma sees me and one who sees me sees the Dhamma. Truly,
seeing the Dhamma, one sees me and seeing me, one sees the Dhamma.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn22.87</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph85">
<content>
<p>I know of no single thing so unworkable as the undeveloped mind. Indeed, the
undeveloped mind is an unworkable thing. I know of no other single thing so
workable as the developed mind. Indeed, the developed mind is a workable
thing.</p>
</content>
<uid>an1.21</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph86">
<content>
<p>Whatever has had to be done by a teacher out of compassion for his disciples
and for their welfare, I have done for you. Here are the roots of the trees,
here are the empty places. Meditate! Do not be slothful, do not be remorseful
later. These are my instructions to you.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn8</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph87">
<content>
<p>Cultivate a friend whose ways are seven. What seven? He gives what is hard
to give, does what is hard to do, bear what is hard to bear, he confesses his
secrets and keeps your secrets, in times of trouble he does not abandon you,
and he does not despise you when you are down.</p>
</content>
<uid>an7.36</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph88">
<content>
<p>How do disciples conduct themselves towards a teacher with love, not
hostility? Concerning this, the compassionate teacher instructs his disciples
in the Dhamma, seeking their welfare and out of compassion, saying: ‘This is
for your welfare and happiness.’ His disciples listen to him, lend an ear,
prepare their minds for profound knowledge, they do not turn aside or move away
from the teacher’s instructions. In this way do disciples conduct themselves
towards a teacher with love, not hostility. Therefore, conduct yourselves
towards me with love, not hostility, and it will be for your welfare and
happiness for a long time.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn122</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>


<epigraph id="epigraph92">
<content>
<p>Who is one’s own best friend, and who is one’s own worst enemy? Those whose
thoughts, speech and actions are evil, they are their own worst enemy. Even if
they were to say: ‘We care about ourselves,’ nevertheless they would still be
their own worst enemy. And why? Because that which one would do to an enemy
they do to themselves.</p>
<p>Those whose thoughts, speech and actions are good, they are their own best
friends. Even if they were to say: ‘We don’t care about ourselves,’
nevertheless they would still be their own best friend. And why? Because that
which one would do to a friend, they do to themselves.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn3.5</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph93">
<content>
<p>Greed, hatred and delusion are unskillful. Whatever the greedy, hating or
deluded person does with body, speech or mind—that is unskillful too. Whatever
one overwhelmed by greed, hatred or delusion and with mind uncontrolled, does
to another, unjustly causing him suffering through punishment, imprisonment,
fine, abuse, banishment, or on the excuse that ‘might is right’—all that is
unskillful, too.</p>
</content>
<uid>an3.69</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph95">
<content>
<p>Do not judge others. Whoever judges others digs a pit for themselves.</p>
</content>
<uid>an6.44</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph96">
<content>
<p>These five trades ought not to be practiced by a layperson. What five? Trade
in weapons, trade in human beings, trade in flesh, trade in alcohol, and trade
in poisons.</p>
</content>
<uid>an5.177</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph99">
<content>
<p>Whatever the Tathāgata utters, speaks and proclaims between the day of his
enlightenment and the day he dies, all that is factual, not otherwise. That is
why he is called the Tathagāta.</p>
</content>
<uid>an4.24</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph104">
<content>
<p>There are these six dangers associated with idleness. Thinking: ‘It’s too
cold,’ one does not work. Thinking: ‘It’s too hot,’ one does not work.
Thinking: ‘It’s too early,’ one does not work. Thinking: ‘It’s too late,’ one
does not work. Thinking: ‘I am too hungry,’ one does not work. Thinking: ‘I am
too full,’ one does not work.</p>
</content>
<uid>dn31</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph105">
<content>
<p>When the good Gotama teaches Dhamma to an assembly in a park he does not
exalt them or disparage them. On the contrary, he delights, uplifts, inspires,
and gladdens that assembly with talk on Dhamma. The sound of the good Gotama’s
voice has eight qualities. It is distinct and intelligible, sweet and audible,
fluent and clear, deep and resonant. Therefore, when he instructs the assembly,
his voice does not go beyond that assembly. After being delighted, uplifted,
inspired and gladdened with talk on Dhamma, the audience rise from their seats
and depart reluctantly, keeping their eyes upon him.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn91</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph106">
<content>
<p>The fool may be known by his deeds. Likewise, the wise one may be known by
his deeds. Wisdom is manifested by one’s deeds.</p>
</content>
<uid>an3.2</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph107">
<content>
<p>The noble disciple who is utterly devoted to and has unshakable faith in the
Tathāgata can have no doubt or wavering concerning the Tathāgata or his
teachings. And it may be expected that such a disciple will live resolute in
energy, always striving to abandon bad qualities and develop good ones, and
that he will be energetic in exerting himself and will not drop the good.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn48.50</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>


<epigraph id="epigraph110">
<content>
<p>One may not be skilled in the knowing others’ thoughts but at least one can
make this resolve: ‘I will be skilled in knowing my own thoughts.’</p>
</content>
<uid>an10.51</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph111">
<content>
<p>Those friends sat down and the Lord gave a progressive talk, that is, on
virtue, on heaven, on the danger, the futility and the disadvantages of sense
pleasures and the advantages of giving them up. Then, when the Lord knew that
their minds were ready, malleable, free from hindrance, uplifted and gladdened,
he explained to them the teaching which is unique to the Buddhas—suffering, its
cause, its overcoming and the way to its overcoming.</p>
</content>
<uid>pi-tv-kd1</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph112">
<content>
<p>There are these six dangers of being addicted to gambling. In winning one
begets hatred, in losing one mourns the loss of wealth, one’s word is not
accepted in court, one is avoided by both friends and officials, and one is not
sought after for marriage because people say a gambler cannot support a
wife.</p>
</content>
<uid>dn31</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph114">
<content>
<p>Jīvaka said: “I have heard this said that it is sublime to abide in love and
the Lord is proof of this because I can see that he abides in love.” The Lord
replied: “Any lust, hatred or delusion which could give rise to ill will has
been abandoned by the Tathāgata, cut off at the root, made like a palm tree
stump, finished so that it cannot grow again in the future. If that is what you
are referring to Jīvaka, then I agree with you.”</p>
</content>
<uid>mn55</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph115">
<content>
<p>Now at that time a certain monk was suffering from dysentery and lay where
he had fallen in his own excrement. … Then the Lord said to Ānanda: “Go and
fetch water so we can wash this monk.” So Ānanda brought water and the Lord
poured it out while Ānanda washed the monk all over. Then taking the monk by
the head and feet, the Lord and Ānanda together carried him and laid him on a
bed. Later, the Lord called the monks together and asked them: “Why monks, did
you not look after that sick monk?”</p>
<p>“Because he was of no use to us, Lord.”</p>
<p>“Monks, you have no mother or father to look after you. If you do not look
after each other who will? He who would nurse me, let him nurse the sick.”</p>
</content>
<uid>pi-tv-kd8</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph118">
<content>
<p>Citta the householder said to the monks: “Suppose a black ox and a white ox
were yoked together. Now, if one were to say that the black ox was the fetter
of the white one, or that the white ox was the fetter of the black one, would
one be speaking rightly?”</p>
<p>“No, they would not, householder. They are fettered by the yoke.”</p>
<p>“Well, in the same way, monks, the eye is not the fetter of objects, nor is
the object the fetter of the eye. Rather, the desire and craving that arises
owing to the pair of them, that is the fetter.”</p>
<p>“Good for you, householder, well said. You have the eye of wisdom that is
consistent with the Buddha’s deep teaching.”</p>
</content>
<uid>sn41.1</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph119">
<content>
<p>Kimbila asked the Lord: “What will be the cause, what the reason why, after
the Tathāgata attains final Nirvāṇa, the good Dhamma will last long?”</p>
<p>“If, after the Tathāgata has attained final Nirvāṇa, the monks and the nuns,
the laymen and the laywomen, live with reverence and care towards the Teacher,
the Dhamma and the Saṅgha, towards samādhi, towards earnestness, and towards
goodwill, then the good Dhamma will last long.”</p>
</content>
<uid>an7.59</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph120">
<content>
<p>Some foolish people here, on being advised by me to give something up, say:
‘But what is this small and insignificant matter? This monk lays too much
stress on minor things.’ And so they do not give up that thing and they cause
dissatisfaction to be nursed against me and those who do desire the training.
This becomes a strong, solid and stout bond for them, a bond not easily worn
away, like a thick block of wood.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn66</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph121">
<content>
<p>At a time when a noble disciple recollects the Buddha, the Dhamma and the
Saṅgha, virtue, generosity and the gods, his mind is free from greed, hatred
and delusion. His mind is straight and fixed upon those things, and with a
straight mind he expresses the gladness of the good, the gladness of the
Dhamma, and the gladness that goes with Dhamma. In one like this gladness
arises, from gladness comes joy, because of joy the body is tranquil, with a
tranquil body one is happy, and the mind of one who is happy goes into
samādhi.</p>
</content>
<uid>an11.11</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph122">
<content>
<p>And what is the factor of exertion for the complete purification of virtues?
In this case, one is virtuous, undertaking and practicing the precepts. This
resolve is called the complete purification of virtue: ‘I will bring to
perfection the purification of virtue if it is incomplete, and if it is
complete I will supplement it here and there with wisdom.’ This is called the
complete purification of virtue. The desire, the effort, the exertion, the
endeavor, the persistence, the mindfulness and attention applied to this is
called a factor in the complete purification of virtue.</p>
</content>
<uid>an4.194</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph124">
<content>
<p>The Tathāgata censures, strongly censures, killing, stealing, sexual
misconduct and lying, saying: ‘Abstain from these things.’ Then say a follower
would think: ‘The Lord in many ways censures, strongly censures, killing,
stealing, sexual misconduct and lying, saying: “Abstain from these things.” Now
I have done such things. That is not well done, it is not good. Moreover, I may
be remorseful when I remember that such deeds cannot be undone.’ Thinking in
this way, he abandons such deeds. In this way he goes beyond evil deeds. By
abandoning killing, he abstains from killing, by abandoning stealing, sexual
misconduct, lying, backbiting, harsh speech, and idle chatter he abstains from
all these things. By abandoning greed, he becomes generous, by abandoning
hatred he becomes kind, and by abandoning wrong view he becomes one with
perfect view. This noble disciple, freed from greed and hatred, not bewildered
but mindful and concentrated, abides suffusing the four quarters of the world,
above, below, across, everywhere, all beings, the whole world with a mind
filled with love, compassion, sympathetic joy and equanimity that is
widespread, grown great.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn42.8</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph125">
<content>
<p>There are two things that burn the conscience. What two? Say a person has
done immoral acts of body, speech or mind, or has failed to do virtuous acts of
the body, speech or mind. When he thinks of this he burns with remorse.</p>
</content>
<uid>an2.3</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph127">
<content>
<p>It is good from time to time to examine one’s own faults; it is good from
time to time to examine another’s faults. It is good from time to time to
examine one’s own attainments; it is good from time to time to examine
another’s attainments.</p>
</content>
<uid>an8.7</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph132">
<content>
<p>There are four kinds of good-hearted people who should be known as true
friends; the helper, the consistent friend, one who gives good counsel, and one
who sympathizes. The helper is a true friend for four reasons. He guards you
when you are off your guard, he guards your property when you are off your
guard, he comforts you when you are afraid, and when something has to be done,
he gives you twice what you require. The consistent friend is a true friend for
four reasons. He tells you his secrets, he keeps the secrets you tell him, in
trouble he does not forsake you, and he would even lay down his life for you.
The friend who gives good counsel is a true friend for four reasons. He
discourages you from doing wrong, he encourages you to do good, he tells you
things you have not heard, and he points out the way to heaven. The friend who
sympathizes is a true friend for four reasons. He is sad at your misfortunes,
he rejoices at your good fortune, he restrains others from speaking ill of you,
and he commends those who speak well of you.</p>
</content>
<uid>dn31</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph133">
<content>
<p>You should recollect beautiful friends like this: ‘It is indeed a gain for
me. Indeed, it is good for me that I have beautiful friends, compassionate,
desiring my welfare, and who mentor and teach me.’</p>
</content>
<uid>an11.13</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph134">
<content>
<p>Truly dangerous are gains, honours and fame. Concerning this, I have known a
person whose mind I have read, who would not deliberately tell a lie even for
the sake of a golden bowl filled with pieces of silver. That same person have I
seen at another time telling lies because his heart was obsessed by gains,
honours and fame. Truly dangerous are gains, honours and fame.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn17.11</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph138">
<content>
<p>The Lord said: “It is like a mother hen with eight, ten or a dozen eggs
which she has sat on properly, warmed properly and hatched properly. Is the
chick which first pierces through the shell with claw and beak to safely emerge
called the eldest chick or the youngest?”</p>
<p>“Being the first, Lord, it is called the eldest.”</p>
<p>“Even so, having pierced through the shell of ignorance for the sake of
beings living in ignorance, egg born and enclosed, I am the first in the world,
utterly enlightened with the unsurpassed enlightenment. I am the eldest, the
highest in the world.”</p>
</content>
<uid>pi-tv-bu-vb-pj1</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>


<epigraph id="epigraph140">
<content>
<p>Vacchagotta said to the Lord: “I have heard it said that you, good Gotama,
teach that charity should only be given to you, not to others, to your
followers, not to the followers of other teachers. Are those who say this
representing your opinion without distorting it? Do they speak according to
your teaching? For indeed, good Gotama, I am anxious not to misrepresent
you.”</p>
<p>The Lord replied: “Vaccha, those who say this are not of my opinion, they
misrepresent me and say what is not true. Truly, whoever discourages another
from giving charity hinders them in three ways. What three? He hinders the
giver from acquiring good, he hinders the receiver from receiving the charity,
and he has already ruined himself through his meanness.”</p>
</content>
<uid>an3.57</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph141">
<content>
<p>I will not treat you the way a potter treats wet clay. Repeatedly
restraining I will speak to you, repeatedly admonishing. The strong heart will
stand the test.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn122</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>


<epigraph id="epigraph145">
<content>
<p>The brahmin Saṅgārava said to the Lord: “Good Gotama, we brahmins perform
the sacrifice and encourage others to do so. Whoever does this creates much
good that benefits many people. But one who goes forth from home into homeless
life as a monk only benefits himself, only calms himself, leads only himself to
Nirvāṇa. I say that such a person is practicing something that benefits only
himself.”</p>
<p>And the Lord said: “Well, brahmin, I will ask you a question, answer as you
think fit. Let us say a Tathāgata arises in the world, a Noble One, a fully
enlightened Buddha, with perfect knowledge and conduct, happily attained, a
knower of the worlds, a guide unsurpassed for people to be tamed, a teacher of
gods and humans, a Buddha, the Lord. And then he says: ‘Come! By my own power
of realization I have attained great happiness as a result of this practice,
this way. You practice it too! By your own powers of realization you too will
attain great happiness as a result of this practice, this way.’ Thus this
teacher teaches Dhamma to many hundreds, many thousands, many hundreds of
thousands of such people. Now brahmin, since this is so, is this going forth
into the homeless life as a monk a practice that benefits only one person or
many people?”</p>
<p>“Good Gotama, it is a practice that benefits many people.”</p>
</content>
<uid>an3.60</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph149">
<content>
<p>Imagine a pool of turbid, stirred up and muddied water. Then, a man with
good vision might stand upon the bank. He could not see the mussels, shells,
pebbles and gravel on the bottom or the fish moving about. And why? Because of
the turbid state of the water. In the same way, it is impossible for one with a
turbid mind to understand either his own benefit or the benefit of others, or
to realize higher states. And why? Because of the turbid state of the mind.
Now, imagine a pool of clear, tranquil and still water. A man with good vision
might stand on the bank. He could see the mussels, shells, pebbles and gravel
on the bottom, and the fish that move about. And why? Because of the untroubled
state of the water. In the same way, it is possible for one with a tranquil
mind to understand his own benefit and the benefit of others, and to realize
higher states. And why? Because of the untroubled state of his mind.</p>
</content>
<uid>an1.46</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph150">
<content>
<p>Those for whom you have sympathy, those with whom you communicate—your
friends, intimates, kinsmen and relations—all should be told about, grounded
in, established in the Four Limbs of Stream-Winning. What are these four? Faith
in the Buddha, faith in the Dhamma, faith in the Saṅgha, and virtue that is
dear to the Noble Ones and conducive to samādhi of mind.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn55.16-17</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph151">
<content>
<blockquote class="gatha">
<p>“In the Bahuka and at Adhikakka,<br/>
At Gayā and in the Sundarika,<br/>
In the Sarassati and at Payaga<br/>
Or in the Bahumati River,<br/>
The fool, though entering constantly,<br/>
Cannot wash away his evil deeds.</p>
<p>What can these rivers do?<br/>
They cannot purify the bad person<br/>
Or one who is intent on evil.<br/>
For the good person, every day is special.<br/>
For the good person, every day is holy.</p>
<p>The good practice good every day.<br/>
Bathe in that and you will protect all beings.</p>
<p>If you speak no lie, do no harm,<br/>
Steal not, if you believe and are generous,<br/>
What can be the good of going to Gayā?<br/>
The water at Gayā is the same as the water at home.”</p>
</blockquote>
</content>
<uid>mn7</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph152">
<content>
<p>And what else should be done? You should think: ‘Our bodily conduct must be
perfectly pure, clear, open, without defect and controlled. But not because of
our being pure will we exalt ourselves or disparage others.’ This is how you
should train yourselves.</p>
</content>
<uid>mn39</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph154">
<content>
<p>Whatever monks possess virtue, samādhi, vision, freedom and knowledge and
vision—just to see them brings much good; just to hear about them brings much
good. To visit them, to sit beside them, to remember what they say, and to
follow them in going forth in the holy life also brings much good.</p>
</content>
<uid>sn46.3</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph158">
<content>
<p>These four who are accomplished in wisdom, who are disciplined, confident,
deeply learned, upholders of Dhamma and who live in accordance with
Dhamma—these four illuminate the Saṅgha. Which four? A monk, a nun, a layman
and a laywoman.</p>
<blockquote class="gatha">
<p>Whoever is wise, disciplined and deeply learned,<br/>
Upholding Dhamma and living according to it,<br/>
They are called ‘Light of the Saṅgha.’<br/>
The monk well-possessed of virtue,</p>
<p>The nun who is widely learned,<br/>
Male and female disciples full of faith—<br/>
It is they who illuminate the Saṅgha.<br/>
‘Light of the Saṅgha’ they are called.</p>
</blockquote>
</content>
<uid>an4.7</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph162">
<content>
<p>There are these four Right Efforts. What four? Concerning this, one
generates desire to prevent the arising of evil, unprofitable states that have
not yet arisen. One makes an effort, sets going energy, lays hold of and exerts
the mind to this end. One generates desire for the abandoning of evil
unprofitable states that have already arisen. One makes an effort, sets going
energy, lays hold of and exerts the mind to this end. One generates desire for
the arising of profitable states that have not yet arisen. One makes an effort,
sets going energy, lays hold of and exerts the mind to this end. And one
generates desire for the persisting, the non-confusion, the further
development, the increase, cultivation and fulfillment of profitable states
that have already arisen. One makes an effort, sets going energy, lays hold of
and exerts the mind to this end.</p>
</content>
<uid>dn22</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph164">
<content>
<p>A teacher should look upon his pupil as a son. A pupil should look upon his
teacher as a father. These two, united by mutual reverence and deference and
living in communion together will achieve increase, growth and progress in this
Dhamma and discipline.</p>
</content>
<uid>pi-tv-kd1</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph165">
<content>
<p>One whose faith in the Tathāgata is settled, fixed, established, firm,
unshaken by any monk or brahmin, by any god, Māra, Brahma or anyone in the
world, can confidently say: ‘I am the true child of the Lord, born of Dhamma,
created by Dhamma, an heir of Dhamma.’</p>
</content>
<uid>dn27</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph167">
<content>
<p>If anyone were to say that just as a person performs a kamma, so is his
experience determined by it, and if this were true, then living the holy life
would not be possible, there would be no opportunity for the overcoming of
suffering. But if anyone were to say that a person performs a kamma that is to
be experienced, so does he experience it, then living the holy life would be
possible, there would be an opportunity for the ending of suffering.</p>
<p>Suppose someone throws a grain of salt into a little cup of water. That
water would be undrinkable. And why? Because the amount of water is small. Now,
suppose someone throws a grain of salt in the River Ganges. That water would not be
undrinkable. And why? Because the amount of water is great.</p>
</content>
<uid>an3.100</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph168">
<content>
<p>Sakka asked the Lord: “Sir, do all monks and brahmins teach the same Dhamma,
practise the same discipline, desire the same thing and pursue the same
goal?”</p>
<p>“No, Ruler of the Gods, they do not. And why not? This world is made up of
many and various elements, and people adhere to one or another of these
elements, and become tenaciously attached to them, saying: ‘This alone is true,
all else is false.’ Therefore, all monks and Brahmins do not teach the same
Dhamma, practice the same discipline, desire the same thing or pursue the same
goal.”</p>
</content>
<uid>dn21</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>

<epigraph id="epigraph169">
<content>
<p>What is the power of sympathy? There are these four bases of sympathy:
generosity, kind speech, doing a good turn and treating all equally. The best
generosity is generosity with the Dhamma. The best kind speech is teaching the
Dhamma again and again to a good and attentive listener. The best good turn is
inciting, encouraging and establishing the ways of faith in the doubting, the
ways of virtue in the unvirtuous, the ways of generosity in the mean, and ways
of wisdom in the foolish. The best equal treatment is the equality between
Stream-Winner and Stream-Winner, between Once-Returner and Once-Returner,
between Non-Returner and Non-Returner, and between Noble One and Noble One.
This is called the power of sympathy.</p>
</content>
<uid>an9.5</uid>
<href></href>
</epigraph>
</epigraphs>
